Okay so today's דף daf is נ"ו. nun vav. We start a
little bit behind, not too bad, on נ"ה nun hey עמוד ב'.
amud bet.
Let's take a look. We are, we are at the very bottom
of נ"ה nun hey עמוד ב'. amud bet. We're not really behind,
two lines, that doesn't even count. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. The גמרא Gemara said that how do we know that
we combine the word לא תעשה lo ta'aseh and לא תעשה חמץ
lo te'aseh chameitz to tell you that תעשה te'aseh is an example
that any sort of any act, any stage of the process, you're
חייב. chayav. And we don't read it like כלל ופרט, klal u'prat,
and one of the reasons that we don't read it like כלל
ופרט klal u'prat is because they're very distant from one another. And
that led into a whole discussion about trying to prove otherwise from
a discussion about the need for שחיטה shechting בצפון bitzafon and a
הוה אמינא havah amina that it would only apply to the שעיר
seir of a נשיא, nasi, which the גמרא Gemara says had nothing
to do with כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, it had to do with
the word אותו, oto, which might have made me think that it
would only be by that. So now we're just going to wrap
up that discussion, let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
והשתא, v'hashta, the first wide line at the very end of that
line, five lines from the bottom, והשתא דנפקא ליה v'hashta d'nafka lei
מן ושחטת את החטאת, min v'shachatat et hachatat, now that we learned
from ושחטת את החטאת v'shachatat et hachatat to tell me that every
חטאת chatat has to be in the north, and it's repeated by
the שעיר נשיא seir nasi to tell me that it's מעכב. me'akev.
אותו למעוטי מאי, oto l'muto mai, why by this שעיר seir of
a נשיא, nasi, by when
a נשיא nasi sins, does it say אותו, oto, it, which implies
like only this applies, this applies only to it and not to
other things? So the גמרא Gemara says למעוטי, l'muto, to exclude אותו
בצפון ואין שעיר נחשון בצפון. oto bitzafon v'ein seir nachshon bitzafon. Only
this goat of a נשיא, nasi, if you would, only this חטאת
chatat of a נשיא nasi is in the north because this is
a one that applies for all future generations, but the one that
נחשון, Nachshon, נחשון Nachshon is used as an example, it really means
all of the נשיאים nesi'im brought on the twelve days starting with
ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan with the inauguration of the משכן.
mishkan. So they brought their various קרבנות korbanot and one of the
things they brought was a חטאת. chatat. Now that's quite bizarre and
this sort of bothers חז"ל. chazal. Whoever heard of bringing a free-will
חטאת? chatat?
So I mean רש"י Rashi points out that, you know, it wasn't
על חטא, al chait, although there are other חטאות chataot which are
not על חטא, al chait, you know, which are for טהרה taharah
purposes. But not so much that it wasn't על חטא al chait
but that it was free-will. So that sort of forces חז"ל chazal
to say how must this really conform to normal law of a
חטאת? chatat? Okay, so it says סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I might have thought הוה אמינא havah
amina since they're about to see that they did סמיכה smichah on
this חטאת chatat that was brought during these twelve days of the
inauguration, maybe it would also require north, קא משמע לן kamasma lan
no.
But they still could have slaughtered it there, they just didn't have
to, right? Or they couldn't?
Oh yeah, you're allowed to do north, right, you're not restricted from
the north. And the answer is quite fascinating because north is not
just a דין חטאת din chatat the same way סמיכה smichah is
not just a דין. din. דינו כקדשי קדשים. dino k'kodashei kodashim. But
nevertheless, you know, they sort of I think it seems like חז"ל
chazal sort of felt although in the end if they'd done דורות
dorot anything that wasn't an exception that's not דורות, dorot, we can't
assume the same laws apply. But I think it's particularly heightened here
because it was a free-will חטאת chatat which is very bizarre.
Okay, so this we'll try to understand, it's קושיא קושיא kusha kusha
that it would have to be anyway. Maybe you don't have to
do it מדין חטאת. mi'din chatat.
Right, that's
the point, the whole this thing, not just that it's not a
traditional
חטאת chatat but there's sort of I think that the whole rule
is an exception. Okay, and you're right, it's quite bizarre where they
come with that, but it's a פלא pela like the exceptional nature
of all of that. Move back this camera a little bit towards
me, sorry. This way, or a three, yeah, like point exactly. Oh,
that way. Thank you, a little bit more. Perfect. Okay, gorgeous. Not
too much. Okay, there we go, perfect. All right, let's go. So
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, וסמיכה גופא מנלן? v'smichah gufah minalan? How do we know
therefore, קא משמע לן kamasma lan that it's not, that it's not
in north? And how do we know סמיכה smichah itself was done
by the שעיר נחשון? seir nachshon? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braita: וסמך ידו על ראש השעיר, v'samach yado al rosh haseir,
you should put the hands on the head of the goat, לרבות
שעיר נחשון לסמיכה. l'rabot seir nachshon l'smichah. So that was said not
obviously by נחשון, Nachshon, that was said by a normal goat that
was brought by a נשיא nasi for sin, the general things said
in the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, but because it says, they could
have just said וסמך ידו על ראשו. v'samach yado al rosho. על
ראש השעיר al rosh haseir means even for another goat brought by
a נשיא. nasi. What other goat was brought by a נשיא? nasi?
The goats that were brought by the נשיאים, nesi'im, חטאת chatat brought
by the נשיאים nesi'im in the חנוכת המשכן, chanukat hamishkan, which had
nothing to do with sin, but basically suggestively, right, it's a חטאת
chatat and it's brought by a נשיא. nasi. And we're talking about
ויקרא Vayikra talks about a חטאת chatat brought by a נשיא. nasi.
So therefore we make that link to say you do סמיכה, smichah,
the extra word על ראש השעיר al rosh haseir and not just
על
ראשו.
al
rosho.
Basically because the נשיא, nasi, you know, talks about in the further
one is like the מלך, melech, isn't it?
Right, well that's how חז"ל chazal understand it. But here it says
נשיא nasi there, it says נשיא nasi there, it's not so bad
that they're learning one from the other.
But they say, you know, the future really would be the נשיא
nasi of a שבט, shevet, would he have to do the same
thing?
Yeah, I think that was some, I'm trying to remember what we
learned in הוריות, Horayot, I believe that yes, that there is discussion
about that. I mean it is a possibility. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ואיבעית אימא רבי יהודה, v'iba'it eima Rabbi Yehuda,
that's what רבי Rabbi says, רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי שמעון אומר,
Rebbe Shimon Omer, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says no. לרבות, Lerabos, top
of מ"ו עמוד א', mem vav amud aleph, לרבות עצי עבודת כוכבים
לסמיכה. lerabos itzei avodas kochavim l'smicha. That it's not, it's not going
to tell you a הלכה Halacha about what applied to the goats
of the twelve-ish, you know, נשיאים, Nesiim, that's not even relevant for
us להלכה. l'halacha. The תורה Torah wouldn't have gone out of its
way to tell you what they did that one time, or what
they had to do that one time. So if it's telling you
something, it's telling you לדורות. l'doros. And it's telling you that there's
another goat that's brought, a goat of a חטאת, chatas, the goats
for עבודה זרה avoda zara that are brought when the בית דין
Beis Din rules incorrectly. Okay, so there too, it's telling you that
that follows the normal rule. Now, that's more obvious, you know, תוספות
Tosafos says give me a break, that's לדורות, l'doros, and that's connected
to other חטאות, chataos, and connected to the חטאת chatas of העלם
דבר. He'elam Davar. For that we presumably know already that it follows
normal rule. The more focus here is the approach of שעיר נחשון
Seir Nachshon and we have no idea what to do with it,
and here it's telling you it's the same for סמיכה. smicha. So
therefore, I would have thought that if it's the same for סמיכה,
smicha, would it be the same for צפון? tzafon? That's what אותו
oso tells you, not that way. So the גמרא Gemara continues, מתקיף
לה רבינא. Maskif lah Ravina. So רבינא Ravina asked, תינח לרבי יהודה,
teinech l'Rebbe Yehuda, that makes sense according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda,
that we needed a פסוק pasuk to tell me that it's not
true for צפון, tzafon, because he said it is true for סמיכה.
smicha. ולרבי שמעון מאי איכא למימר, U'l'Rebbe Shimon mai ika l'meimar, according
to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon what do you do with the word
אותו? oso?
So אמר ליה מר זוטא בריה דרבי מרי לרבינא, amar lei Mar
Zutra brei d'Rebbe Mari l'Ravina, so it said back to רבינא, Ravina,
רבי יהודה נמי, Rebbe Yehuda nami, wait a minute, I don't even
buy it for
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. מאי דאירבי אירבי ומאי דלא אירבי לא אירבי.
Mai d'israbis israbis u'mai d'lo israbis lo israbis. You don't need אותו
oso to exclude north. This whole case of the שעיר נחשון Seir
Nachshon is such an exception that my basic stance is, unless you
prove to me something is included, I'm going to assume it doesn't
follow normal rule. And again, that's quite fascinating. You know, it's one
thing to say we don't learn שעה מדורות, sha'ah m'doros, is something
applied to an exceptional situation, we don't say we're going to assume
it's going to apply to all future situations. But here, it's not
we're learning from the exception trying to make it a rule. We
have a general rule. This has been named as a member of
one of that category, although it has some exceptional features, right? It's
still a, and the גמרא Gemara is insistence that we're going to
take a stance that I can't assume any laws apply to it
unless it's explicit. Right? That is quite interesting and again I would
say it's not just that it's בשעה, b'sha'ah, but it's also that
it's a free-will חטאת. chatas. Okay, so he says I don't even
buy it according to
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. מאי דאירבי אירבי ומאי דלא אירבי לא אירבי.
Mai d'israbis israbis u'mai d'lo israbis lo israbis. If you have a
special פסוק pasuk to include something like סמיכה, smicha, fine, that's included.
But if you don't have a פסוק pasuk to include something like
צפון, tzafon, it won't be included. So even according to him you
don't need the word אותו oso to exclude north. Because the stance
will be, unless you explicitly include something, we're going to assume it's
excluded. וכי תימא אי לאו מיעטיה קרא הוה אמינא תיתי מבניינא אב.
V'chi teima ee lo miateich kra hava amina teisi m'binyan av. And
you'll say, oh well, you know, no, maybe not. Maybe if it
were not for the אותו, oso, I would have learned out סמיכה
smicha from other חטאות. chataos. I would have said, let's just say,
you know, it's like every other חטאת, chatas, it needs סמיכה. smicha.
Maybe my stance would have been fundamentally to assume it's the same
unless it's excluded. That's obviously not true. אטו סמיכה גופיה ליכתוב קרא
מיניה ותיתי מבניינא אב. Atu smicha gufei lichtov kra minei v'teisi m'binyan
av.
Then why did I need a פסוק pasuk to include סמיכה? smicha?
Why couldn't the פסוק pasuk be in silence and I could have
said that this חטאת chatas that the נחשון Nachshon brought and the
נשיאים Nesiim brought has סמיכה smicha like every other חטאת? chatas? So
what he's basically saying is even according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
that says it does have סמיכה, smicha, the fact that you needed
a פסוק pasuk to include סמיכה smicha tells me that my point
of departure is no normal laws apply to it. If that's my
point of departure, even according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, you don't
need אותו oso to exclude צפון. tzafon. I naturally assume צפון tzafon
is excluded. אלא, Ella, what's our assumption? אלא שעה מדורות לא ילפינן.
Ella sha'ah m'doros lo yalpinan. We don't learn from a, you know,
something that applied only one time in history for general, for all
future generations. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, that's why we didn't know סמיכה
smicha and we needed a פסוק pasuk for סמיכה. smicha. הכא נמי,
Hacha nami, so when it comes to north as well, we don't
need a פסוק pasuk to exclude it, we just don't have anything
to include it. And we can't assume it's going to be north.
And the גמרא Gemara is fine with that, the גמרא Gemara basically
says you're right. So that's not what אותו oso is coming to
do. So again, what's fascinating here is it's not, north is not
about being a חטאת, chatas, north is about being קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim. סמיכה Smicha is not about חטאת. chatas. And nevertheless, this case
is so exceptional that the גמרא Gemara is saying that unless we
have an explicit פסוק, pasuk, we can't even assume the basic component.
Okay, so fine, so you don't have north. But now you have
the still the question: what do we need the אותו oso to
exclude since this was naturally excluded anyway? So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: אלא אותו טעון צפון ואין השוחט עומד בצפון. Ella oso taun
tzafon v'ein hashocheit omeid b'tzafon. You have to slaughter it, ושחט
אותו, v'shachat oso, the animal has to be in the north, but
the שוחט shocheit doesn't have to be. But we know that already.
So we're going to discuss if we know that already. Okay, so
let's, but the logic here is, just to remind us, remember שחיטה
shechita is not an עבודה. avodah. So the idea that, and so
the שוחט shocheit doesn't have to be in the north, the שוחט
shocheit can even be חוץ למקדש. chutz l'mikdash. Right? He can be
standing, well, he doesn't have to be that long because he can
be standing in the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim because then just over
the line. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara had a long life, a
knife, but it's the שוחט shocheit is not an
עבודה. avodah. but at least we could say that the animal status
is being designated at the moment of שחיטה shechitah, *shechita* and designated
as, you know, it's sort of the שחיטה shechitah, *shechita* at the
level of קדושה kedushah... *kedusha* and its designation as what type and
obviously the מחשבה *machshava* matters by סמיכה *shmicha*, so it's sort of
a full designation there as קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim. *kodshei kodashim*, whatever
occurs at the moment of שחיטה shchitah *shechita*. So obviously, it has
to be in the place where קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim? *kodshei kodashim*
belong, it has to be in the north. But the שוחט shocheit
*shochet*, we're not focusing on the act itself, and therefore he does
not have to be in the north, and that's what אותו oto
*oto* tells me.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute, like Michael says, we
know that from somewhere else. אותו oto *Oto* and not the שוחט
shocheit *shochet* in the north. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מהא
דבי אחי נפקא *meha d'bei Achi nafka*. We know it from a
teaching of רבי אחי *Rabbi Achi*. What does רבי
אחי *Rabbi Achi* say? דתניא detanya, *D'tanya*, רבי אחי *Rabbi Achi* אומר
*omer*, ושחט אותו oto על ירך המזבח ha-mizbe'ach, צפנה *v'shachat oto al
yerech hamizbeach tzafona*. You shall slaughter it on the side of the
מזבח Mizbe'ach *mizbeach* to the north. מה תלמוד לומר *Ma talmud lomar*?
What do we learn from this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? לפי שמצינו במקבל
Bemekabel? שעומד בצפון ומקבל בצפון *Lefi shematzinu b'mekabel she'omed b'tzafon u'mekabel b'tzafon*.
We know when you catch the blood, you're both catching it in
the north, the vessels in the north, and you're standing in the
north. Right, you could imagine you're standing just over the line, and
the vessel is in the north and you're in the south or
whatever. No, you have to be in the north as well. ואם
עמד בדרום וקיבל בצפון פסול *V'im amad b'darom v'kibel b'tzafon pasul*. And
if you were in the south and the vessel was in the
north, right, then it would be invalid. So it's not only where
it's happening, it's where you are. So once that's true, יכול אף
af זה כן *yachol af zeh ken*? Maybe the same requirement would
be by שחיטה shchitah. *shechita*? Okay, תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, that's why
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says ושחט אותו oto, *v'shachat oto*, אותו oto
בצפון ולא השוחט צריך להיות עומד בצפון *oto b'tzafon v'lo hashochet tzarich
l'hiyot omed b'tzafon*. Only the animal has to be in the north,
not the שוחט shocheit *shochet*. So it's not saying where we know
the other things, that you have to be in the north from
catching the blood, that's not our interest right now. But anyway, from
אותו oto... *oto* we learn that only the animal has to be
in the north. That's by an עולה olah, *ola*. Presumably, whatever applies
by one applies by the other, especially because the Torah says where
do you, what do you do by a חטאת chata'at? *chatas*? במקום
אשר תשחט העולה *B'makom asher tishachat ha'ola*. That the Torah is always
comparing the שחיטה shchitah. *shechita* of חטאת chata'at *chatas* to the עולה
olah *ola*. And the עולה olah *ola*, as I told you before,
is always sort of the base of, you know, the prime קרבן
korban, *korban* of the מזבח *mizbeach*. It's מזבח העולה *mizbach ha'ola*. It's
the first one opened up in ויקרא Vayikra, *Vayikra*, the קרבן korban
התמיד *korban hatamid*, the first קרבן korban, *korban* brought out is an
עולה olah, *ola*. Everything's in reference to the עולה olah, *ola*. So
anyway, we already know by the עולה olah *ola* that that's in
the north and not the שוחט shocheit. *shochet*. We don't need the
אותו oto *oto* by the חטאת chata'at *chatas* to tell me the
same thing. So let's take a look how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
responds to that. אלא Ela, *Ela*, okay, אותו oto בצפון
*oto b'tzafon*, you're right, and we already know only you don't, the
שוחט shocheit *shochet* doesn't have to be in the north. But here's
what it tells me: only a חטאת chata'at *chatas* of an animal
has to be in the north, ואין בן עוף בצפון *v'ein ben
of b'tzafon*, but a bird חטאת chatas *chatas* does not have to
be in the north. Now the Torah never says it. Right, the
Torah doesn't say you slaughter the bird חטאת chatas *chatas* in the
north, but I might have made some type of a link, חטאת-חטאת
*chatas-chatas*, maybe it requires north? No, only an animal חטאת chatas *chatas*
in the north, not a bird one. Okay, that sounds like a
good answer. Let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* responds. סלקא דעתך
אמינא salka datcha amina, *Salka daitach amina*, why would I have thought
the bird would be in the north? I might have thought, ליתי
בקל וחומר *leisei b'kal vachomer*, let's make a קל וחומר kal vachomer,
*kal vachomer* from בן צאן *ben tzon*, from a sheep which is
a חטאת *chatas*. מה בן צאן שלא קבע לו כהן kohen *Mah
ben tzon shelo kava lo kohen*, a sheep that does not require
a כהן kohen *kohen*, right, because שחיטה shchitah. *shechita* is כשירה בזר
*kshera b'zar*, you don't need to be a כהן kohen *kohen*. So
therefore we don't, in the act of שחיטה shchitah. *shechita* itself, here's
the point, it's not just a technical way in which it's more
lenient, central to the act of שחיטה shchitah, *shechita* itself, we have
fewer demands. We don't require that a כהן kohen *kohen* do the
act of שחיטה *shechita*. And nevertheless, what's the one thing we do
demand by an animal חטאת *chatas*? That it be in the north,
even though we don't demand that the כהן kohen *kohen* do it.
שלא קבע לו כהן kohen קבע לו צפון *Shelo kava lo kohen
kava lo tzafon*, the sheep requires north. בן עוף שקבע לו כהן
kohen *Ben of shekava lo kohen*, a bird חטאת *chatas* which we
know you need a כהן kohen *kohen*, right, because the כהן Kohen
*kohen* slaughters it with his fingernail, so the Torah is more demanding
in terms of the act of שחיטה *shechita* itself. If it's more
demanding שקבע לו כהן Kohen. אינו דין שיקבע לו צפון eino din
sheyikva lo tzafon? *shekava lo kohen eino din sheyikba lo tzafon*? How
much more so would it need north? So I might have thought
that a bird would need north because the sheep needs north and
I could have made a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* and
therefore it says, no, no, אותו oto *oto*, only the sheep and
not the bird.
Yeah, you know, we've already been through all these things, I guess,
so it doesn't say much because, you know, how we can't really
compare...
Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say it. Okay,
so just hold on, alright. Yes, I mean, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
does sometimes draw on other descriptions and repeat some of them. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute, as Michael sort of
intuited, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מה לבן צאן שכן
קבע לו כלי *mah l'ben tzon sheken kava lo kli*? One minute,
a sheep you're saying it made less demand because it didn't require
a כהן Kohen. *kohen*. But you know what it did require? It
did require a כלי *kli*, a knife. Now a lot of ראשונים
Rishonim *rishonim* say that also means a כלי שרת *kli sharet*. There's
a debate actually whether you need a כלי שרת *kli sharet* for
שחיטה *shechita* of the animals in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* because
it's not an עבודה *avoda* etc. But at least you do need
a כלי *kli*, you need a knife. And by the שחיטה *shechita*
of the כהן Kohen *kohen*, you use the finger itself. Now how
do you define that? And you say מליקה *melika*, right, thank you.
So do you say that that means that there's more of a
demand on the כהן *kohen* because it requires this whole funny way
of doing it, it has to use his body? You could translate
that as a higher demand, but you could also say no, the
fact that you require... very specific vessel can also be seen as
a specific new type of a ritual demand, especially if it's כלי
שרת, and therefore you can't, you cannot make a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer. because obviously a sheep is different than a bird, ways more
lenient, ways more strict, and you cannot learn from one to the
other.
Okay, so, okay, you're right. Fine. I wouldn't have applied it to
bird and I don't need a פסוק pasuk to exclude that. אלא,
ela, okay, אותו בצפון ואין פסח בצפון. oto batzafon ve'en pesach batzafon.
It is in the north and not a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
Okay, why would I have thought a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach would
have been in the north? It's קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, so let's
take a look. גמרא Gemara says one minute, you don't even need
that פסוק pasuk פסח, Pesach, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב נפקא, Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov nafka, we already know פסח Pesach is not in the
north from the teaching of רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov, דתניא, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer,
יכול יהא הפסח טעון צפון. yakhol yehe hapessach te'un tzafon. Maybe the
פסח Pesach would require north, even though it's קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim?
Why? ודין הוא, Vadin hu, I make a קל וחומר. ומה עולה
שלא קבע לה זמן בשחיטה קבע לה צפון, uma olah shelo kave'a
lah zman bishchitah, kave'a lah tzafon, this is the point like every
קרבן, korban almost every קרבן korban, is not strictly more or less
weighty, more or less holy or strict, each one has different characteristics.
So פסח Pesach maybe is, makes more demands, why? Because פסח Pesach
can only be done one time during the year and only a
very specific time, like in the afternoon, so it's a more weighty
more קרבן, korban? more demands. מה פסח ש... ma pesach she... where
were we? יכול יהא... yakhol yehe... מה פסח... ma pesach... so where
were we? ודין הוא מה עולה שלא קבע לה זמן בשחיטה. vadin
hu, ma olah shelo kava lah zman bishchitah. I don't care when
you שחט shacht an עולה, olah, you bring an עולה olah? anytime
during the day and any day. קבע לה צפון, kava lah tzafon,
nevertheless there's a demand to be done in the north. פסח שקבע
לו זמן לשחיטתו, pesach shekava lo zman lishchitato, פסח Pesach that the
תורה Torah said a specific time for שחט-ing shacht it, right, on
the 14th in the
afternoon, אינו דין din שיקבע לו צפון? Maybe it has also similar,
it has the same more demands, it has north? So פסח Pesach
is essentially weightier, there's a specific more demands on how you do
the שחיטה, when you do the שחיטה, so maybe it also has
to be in the north. No, no, that's not a good קל
וחומר. מה לעולה שכן כליל, ma le'olah sheken kalil, an עולה olah
is weightier in other ways, it's fully burned. So you can't say
that if it's required by an עולה, olah, it's required by פסח.
Pesach. Okay, מחטאת, mechata'at, how about a חטאת? That's not fully burned
and that requires a north? No, מה לחטאת שכן מכפרת על חייבי
כריתות. ma lechata'at sheken mechaperet al chayvei kritot. חטאת is weightier than
a פסח Pesach and that it atones, so what's required by a
חטאת you can't assume is required by פסח. Pesach. Okay, מאשם, me'asham,
how about an אשם? asham? That doesn't atone for חייבי כרת? chayvei
karet? No, מה לאשם שכן קדשי קדשים. ma le'asham sheken kodshei kodshim.
It might not atone for חייבי כרת, chayvei karet, but it atones
for other things, and even bracketing atone, it's קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodshim
Okay, how do we know by the way קדשי קדשים? kodshei kodshim,
Normally קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim we say means it's in the north,
but that would be begging the question, so the basic way that
I've also often heard is the...
what? We have a תורת העולה והחטאת torat ha'olah ve'hachata'at that links
everything.
Yeah, that's true, the גמרא Gemara draws on that very, very selectly.
Anyway, קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodshim, the basic way to understand it, I
think conceptually and also to know what the rule is, if קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodshim, never leave the מקדש. Mikdash. Once they get in
the מקדש Mikdash and get שחט-ed, shacht they never leave. They either
get burnt on the מזבח or they get eaten by the כהנים.
Kohanim. And that's the whole idea, קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodshim they remain
in the full קדש. kodesh. קדשים קלים kodshim kalim can go out
of the מקדש Mikdash and into ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so these are
all קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodshim so therefore they're all weighty in that
way, so just... and that's the rule, קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim need
north, קדשים קלים kodshim kalim don't need north. So even if a
פסח Pesach has certain things that's stricter about it, like that it
has to be שחט-ed shacht at a particular time, you can't assume
what's true about קדשי קדשים kodashim. is true about קדשים קלים. kodshim
kalim. Okay, so there was no הוה אמינא havah amina by פסח.
Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says מכולהו נמי שכן קדשי קדשים. mikulu
nami sheken kodshei kodshim. That's true about everything that's north is קדשי
קדשים kodashim, and there was never a הוה אמינא havah amina to
apply it to a פסח. Pesach. So you can't say אותו oto.
tells me you don't need north by birds or you don't need
north by פסח Pesach because I never would have had a good
argument to have required north by birds or פסח. Pesach. So you
don't need אותו oto to exclude it. So we're back to our
question, what is אותו oto excluding that it says that you שחט
shacht this goat of the נשיא, nasi, of the normal חטאת of
the נשיא nasi in the north, why does it emphasize it? What's
it excluding? So the גמרא Gemara goes back to what it said
before. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא לעולם כידאמרינן מעיקרא. ela le'olam
kider'amrina me'ikara. You're right, it's like we said originally. אותו בצפון ואין
השוחט בצפון. oto batzafon ve'ein hashocheit batzafon. It's telling the that the
animal has to be in the north and you're not in the
north. Now didn't we learn it from the פסוק pasuk by an
עולה, אותו, oto that says by the עולה you שחט shacht it
in the north? So the גמרא Gemara says ודקשיא לך מדרב אחייא
נפקא, ve'deka'shya lakh mid'Rav Achya nafka, you were bothered that don't we
already know that from רב אחייא Rav Achya that only the animal
has to be in the north and you don't have to be
in the
north? רב אחייא לאו לימוד השוחט בצפון דאתא. Rav Achya lav limmud
hashocheit batzafon de'ata. רב אחייא Rav Achya is not emphasizing the שוחט
shocheit doesn't have to be in the north, so what's he emphasizing?
אלא הכי קאמר, ela hakhi ka'amar, אין השוחט בצפון אבל מקבל בצפון,
ein hashocheit batzafon aval mekabel batzafon, the
one who catches has to be in the north, meaning get through,
remember what רב אחייא Rav Achya did. He contrasted the שוחט shochet.
to the one who caught the blood. The שוחט shochet. doesn't have
to be in the north, אותו oto. means only the animal and
not him, but the מקבל mekabel does have to be in the
north. Now the simple statement of רב אחייא Rav Achya was he
was telling you a חידוש chiddush about the שוחט. Although the מקבל
mekabel has to be in the north, the שוחט does not. The
גמרא Gemara is just flipping it, that רב אחייא Rav Achya is
sort of starting from the other direction. We take it for granted
that the שוחט does not have to be in the north, how
do we know that from
the אותו... oto How about the מקבל? mekabel? Does he have to
be in the north? Yeah, מקבל mekabel does have to be in
the north. Why? Because the Torah says אותו again by חטאת to
tell you it's in a way it's just by שחיטה that I
allow you to focus on the animal and not the person. But
by everything else, the כהן has to be in the north as
well. Okay, not everything else, just the קבלה. kabalah. Obviously הולכה וזריקה
holacha vezrika you're leaving the north. The קבלה kabalah is what happened
at the moment of the שחיטה. Okay, so here אותו is not
telling you the דין that it's not required by שחיטה. It's telling
you the reverse. It's only an exception by שחיטה. It is required
by קבלה kabalah and that's what you need the second אותו to
tell you.
היכא דגמרינן דורות משה Heicha degamrinan doros Mosheh essentially.
No, אותו. No, you want אותו by an עולה, one אותו by
the
not the דנשיא, denasi, the דחטאת חטאת, di chatas chatas, the דחטאת
נשיא, di chatas nasi, the end of ויקרא, Vayikra אשר נשיא יחטא.
Asher nasi yecheta. Right.
Oh, so it's not talking about the דנשיא? denasi?
No, no, we've thrown out the דנשיא. denasi. Okay, but we're still
trying to figure out what do you need the אותו for a
classic חטאת for the נשיא nasi if you what is it telling
me only it? So telling you only the not only the animal,
not the שוחט. Don't we know it from עולה? Yeah, but from
עולה actually we're saying that it's only in that's only true by
שחיטה. The reverse is true and it's not true by קבלה. kabalah.
So the גמרא Gemara, says one minute.
אלא הכי קאמר שוחט כשר ובמאי דפסל במקבל פוסל. Ela hachi ka'amar
shochet kasher ubmai d'pasal b'mekabel poseil. במקבל? מולקח ולקח נפקא. Milakach velakach
nafka. It says ולקח מדם הפר Velakach midam hapar and that the
גמרא Gemara understands that that refers to קבלה. kabalah. And since it
says you take that and it's they understand that you're taking from
where the פר par is standing. ולקח מדם הפר, Velakach midam hapar,
so if the פר par is in the north, you're taking in
the north and you're standing in the north. So and we learn
from the extra ו vav
to tell you that it's not just the קבלה kabalah takes place,
but you the כהן are also in the north. ולקח Lakach means
the קבלה kabalah is in the north. ולקחה Ulakachah is where the
פר par is. ולקח Velakach means that the כהן is there with
it in the north. So the גמרא Gemara says לוקח ולקח לא
משמע ליה. Lakach velakach la mashma lei. No, he does the extra
ו vav doesn't do it for him. So he gets it from
the אותו. So all of this was wrapping up a big digression.
What do we need the אותו for the חטאת of a נשיא
nasi for? To tell me that only the animal has to be
in the north, not the שוחט. Don't we know it from somewhere
else? Yes, we do know it from somewhere else, but they are
telling me that's true by שחיטה, but by קבלה kabalah the כהן
has to be in the north. All of this was a big
digression about
כלל ופרט המרוחקים זה מזה klal ufrat hamruchakim ze mize to basically
get to the bottom line that although one פסוק pasuk in ויקרא
says
לא תעשו חמץ lo te'asu chametz
and in צו Tzav it says לא תעשה חמץ. lo te'aseh chametz.
We don't read this as a כלל ופרט. klal ufrat. We read
it as something that was היה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד. hayah
baklal veyatza min haklal lelamed. So basically all acts of making something,
of making the bread, if the bread is חמץ chametz you transgress,
but we don't it's not just one transgression of תעשה, te'aseh, but
every separate act is considered a separate transgression and that we've learned
out from עשיה. asiyah. And now we finally get to turn our
attention to back to the making of the מנחה minchah and the
איסור issur of making it חמץ. chametz. So let's take a look
now at the two dots. וחייב על לישתה ועל עריכתה ועל אפייתה.
Vechayav al lishatah ve'al arichatah ve'al afiyatah. This was the משנה. mishnah.
You transgress for
anyway, okay.
So וחייב על לישתה ועל עריכתה ועל אפייתה.
Vechayav al lishatah ve'al
arichatah ve'al afiyatah. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: אפאה, Afah, if
you did bake it, לוקה שתים.
lokei shtayim.
You get two lashes, two sets of lashes. Why?
אחת על עריכתה
ואחת על אפייתה.
Achas al arichatah ve'achas al
afiyatah.
One for baking, obviously, but one also for עריכה. arichah. עריכה Arichah
is sort of fashioning the shape of the bread. Okay, so fitting
it to the form.
No, so his חידוש chiddush is you're not getting it for having
done the עריכה arichah and then do the אפיה. afiyah. Then he
wouldn't be telling you anything. He's saying you walk in, you Michael,
you've been going ahead and you've been doing the עריכה. arichah. You
get whatever lashes you're getting for doing it as חמץ. chametz. Okay,
maybe you didn't maybe it's not חמץ chametz yet. I take it
from you and now I'm waiting around and now it becomes חמץ.
chametz. So you are or are not חייב. chayav. It doesn't matter.
I take I come and I take the bread, actually in theory
it could be me too, I could be working it and doing
all this stuff before חמץ. chametz. And then I let it become
חמץ chametz and now I'm going to bake it. Okay, so whatever
it is, I walk in on the scene at the moment of
baking. I did because somebody else has been doing it or because
only now did it become חמץ. chametz. And I put it in
the oven. Okay, so he says that act of putting it in
the oven is not just an act of עשיה. asiyah. That act
of putting it in the oven is also עריכה. arichah. Now why
is it עריכה? arichah? First of all, I'm not enough of a
baker to tell you or and I don't know enough about baking
in 2,000 years ago to tell you exactly what was done, but
obviously there was the גמרא Gemara often talks about like its fashioning
against the wall of the oven. It talks about רדיית הפת בתנור
rediyat hapat batanur it's sort of like this what do they call
that? tanur type of a thing, you know, that they stick it
on the wall of the oven. So basically, what it seems that
it's saying is is not just that רש"י's Rashi a little bit
ambiguous how רש"י Rashi interprets it. It could be רש"י Rashi could
be saying that just the very fact that it bakes since that
finishes the form, then that itself is considered a type of an
עריכה Arikha as well. But it's easier to understand that it that
there's actually that since I'm putting it on the wall of the
oven and that's also part of creating its shape, so even then
before it actually starts baking there was an עריכה Arikha that took
place. And a way to conceptually see this is, let's say the
fire went out in the middle and it never and it never
and it never baked, right? So therefore the act of עריכה Arikha
would still have taken place because I've given it the shape that
it needs, right? The אפייה Afia essentially meaning my act all took
place at one moment but the אפייה Afia requires that it keep
on baking, the עריכה Arikha took place, I did an additional עריכה
Arikha by putting it into, you know, against, in the wall of
the oven. So two acts of עריכה Arikha so to speak. Well
there's the act of עריכה Arikha like shaping it before and then
when you actually put it in the wall of the oven there's
some type of little עריכה Arikha then as well.
So if I did the act of עריכה Arikha before and then
you put it in the oven but there was no fire and
then someone put a fire,
right, that would be a good example, right, correct, that's a nice
example. Okay, again רש"י Rashi makes it sound like a little bit
that maybe maybe the very act of baking itself since it gives
it it creates its final form is also considered עריכה, Arikha, but
it's easier I think to learn it this way which is more
or less what תוספות Tosfot is saying that there's actually a physical
עריכה Arikha that takes place in the putting in the oven.
This is also things that we discussed by you know רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam when we were talking about the ovens being grease on
the walls, the bread's actually being fitted into the ovens and having
direct contact with the walls of the oven in particular.
Exactly, exactly. The wall itself of the oven becomes almost like a
mold, a baking pan in a mold. So putting it in there
is a type of an עריכה. Arikha.
That's what they call אוצמא, otzma, right?
What, אוצמא? otzma? Well that's also the רדייה, Rediya, how do you
get it out without collapsing. Right, exactly. So that's what he's saying.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ואמרת מאפין מיוחד לשמה
דיחידי וחייבין אלא בפני עצמה, v'amarta mafi'in meyuchad l'shmah d'yachidi v'chayavin ela
bifnei atzmah,
when we use אפייה Afia as the model for how the תורה
Torah makes you know to sort of the paradigm that you transgress
in anything like אפייה, Afia, we said אפייה Afia is a separate
stage and you get lashed for אפייה Afia by itself. Now if
you're telling me that every act of אפייה Afia essentially other than
Michael's ingenious idea of lighting the fire, but anyway, but every act
of אפייה Afia fundamentally includes two stages, how can we use this
as a paradigm to say you're חייב chayav for every single stage?
If really it has only two, it always has two stages with
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's
not difficult, הא דעריך הוא ואפה הוא הא דעריך חבריה ויהב ליה
ואפה. ha d'arikh hu v'afah hu ha d'arikh chavreih v'yahav lei v'afah.
One is you did the עריכה Arikha and the אפייה, Afia, and
the other is somebody else did the עריכה Arikha and you did
the אפייה. Afia. Now what does this mean? So you'd be inclined
to say what it means is that if somebody else does the
עריכה Arikha and I do the אפייה Afia then
then I've only transgressed one, right? But then then the whole statement
doesn't mean anything. Then you're saying oh if you do עריכה Arikha
and אפייה Afia you transgress twice. Frankly I could have figured that
out myself, right? So there's no חידוש chiddush of this statement. So
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfot both resist that answer and they say
no, no, it means the opposite of what I would have thought.
If somebody else does the עריכה Arikha and I do the אפייה
Afia that's where I get twice. If I do the עריכה Arikha
and the אפייה Afia then what happens is, okay why do I
get twice? Michael did the עריכה, Arikha, I did the אפייה Afia
for the reason we said. He gives me the bread, I put
it in the oven, the very putting in the oven is not
just an אפייה, Afia, there's also a little bit of an עריכה
Arikha going on there as well. Where do you get אפייה Afia
existing by itself? If I'm doing the עריכה Arikha and the אפייה
Afia then what we do is when I'm putting it in the
oven that little fitting we incorporate that עריכה Arikha to my previous
עריכה. Arikha. I'm finishing up my previous עריכה Arikha and then we
sort of say conceptually that you know what I've done here, I've
finished one עריכה Arikha and now I'm doing an אפייה. Afia. And
therefore when we say that you're חייב chayav for אפייה Afia בפני
עצמה bifnei atzmah it means in this type of a case we
only wouldn't have looked at the עריכה Arikha as significant, we would
have seen that as an end of the previous process and the
תורה Torah even says here you know that there's still you're still
חייב chayav just for the אפייה Afia as a separate.
Would we go so far as to the person who did the
first forming actually isn't even חייב chayav because it wasn't the final
formation?
No, that we never say. I mean at least the ראשונים rishonim
they would say that. Right, no, but it's not negligible. I mean
but you're right, I mean so if you have to say מעשה
יחידי maaseh yechidi it means everything has to begin and be finished.
But no, that's not the suggested answer and certainly you know the
language
that's עריכה Arikha אפייה Afia suggests the classic עריכה Arikha you're חייב
chayav for. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara. says. Let's take
a look. So that's how you get these different stages. תנו רבנן,
Tano Rabbanan, now we are going to have a fascinating question about
and I'll just introduce it for one second because it's going to
sound like it's completely irrelevant
that the idea that you're חייב chayav על לישתו ועל עריכתו ועל
אפייתו. al lishato v'al arikhato v'al afiyato. Now you could have you
know presumably means not just that if you at any stage allow
it to become חמץ chametz you're חייב, chayav, but presumably as we're
already saying here if you could be חייב chayav שתיים shtayim the
person doing the עריכה Arikha is חייב, chayav, the person doing אפייה
Afia is חייב, chayav, it means that
even though it already is חמץ. chametz. So that is a חידוש
chiddush because we're not saying that the prohibition is having let it
become חמץ chametz and once you've had some חמץ, chametz, that's it,
nobody else can let it become חמץ, chametz, it already is חמץ.
chametz. Okay, no, we're saying the prohibition is being involved in the
making of it as חמץ. chametz. So even if you're not to
blame for it being חמץ, chametz, you're still involved in making it
חמץ chametz and it's not a problem. The גמרא's Gemara going to
call that המחמץ אחר מחמץ. hamachmetz achar machmetz. You allowed it to
become חמץ chametz after somebody else did. Part of the reason you're
חייב chayav though is because the way we're framing the transgression is
not don't let it become חמץ chametz but don't make it as
חמץ. chametz. Okay, but then it raises questions in other similar things.
How much are we concerned about the act or how much are
we concerned about what has resulted from it and would you continue
to transgress if the result was already there? So I'll give you
one nice example that isn't in the גמרא, Gemara that's an important
discussion practically, about a כהן becoming טמא למת. tamei lameis. Okay, it's
in another גמרא Gemara in נזיר. Nazir. Okay, if a כהן is
already טמא מת, tamei meis, which is presumably all of our כהנים
kohanim are טמאי מת, tmei meis, כהן is born in a hospital,
let's say there's a morgue, whatever, I mean it's not always that
they're טמאי מת, tmei meis, let's assume he's טמא מת, tmei meis,
so is it אסור assur for him to now become טמא למת
tamei lameis again? Right, is it the act of being טמא למת
tamei lameis or is it having now made himself טמא, tamei, and
therefore having done it once he's already טמא tamei is not significant?
So the גמרא Gemara in נזיר, Nazir, so as you might imagine
כהנים kohanim don't go into בתי קברות batei kvaros or even if
they went for a relative they don't go again, so it is
אסור, assur, but even there there's a question in the גמרא Gemara
why is that or in the ראשונים why is that true. Is
it because even if you're already טמא, tamei, even if you're already
טמאי מת, tmei meis, when you actually become טמא tamei again, at
that moment of contact, it's a higher level of טומאה. tumah. So
you actually are changing your status during that moment of contact. Right,
yeah, because you're in טומאה
בחיבורין tumah bechiburin and therefore things that your clothes that you're wearing
are becoming an אב, av, you know, etc., so it is a
slightly higher level. Or is it no, even if it were no
higher level, the איסור issur is to do the act of being
טמא tamei even if it doesn't change your הלכה halakhah status. Okay,
so anyway, there's like a nice example and we're now going to
see other cases about that. Is the emphasis on the result and
therefore once the result, the bad result's already there, what you're doing
is not so bad, or is the problem in the act and
therefore even if it's already messed up, you cannot continue to do
that
same act?
Like the כהן and the איסור issur of חמץ, chametz, the result
happening even if it's passively in terms of your action is still
a problem.
Becoming טמא? tamei? Right. Yeah. So how do you know it's a
problem if you're already טמא? tamei? Huh?
No, I understand the question, but I could have tried to make
a conclusion about חמץ chametz that oh, if I did the formation
prior to it becoming חמץ chametz and I just walk away and
no one else has touched it again, but it becomes חמץ, chametz,
that that's not a problem but I see that that is a
problem.
Well, no, actually, that is a very important question which we have
not addressed. Since we are saying that the problem is מעשה ידי
משעת עריכה ma'aseh yadei meishat arichah etc., you could imagine that actually
it becomes חמץ chametz and nobody has transgressed because I did the
לישה lishah and while I'm doing the לישה lishah it's not, you
know, it's not חמץ, chametz, I'm doing the לישה. lishah. Now let's
say it's somebody else's job to do the עריכה. arichah. So, you
know, I walk away, I'm done, I say you know the other
guy's supposed to show up, he's two minutes late, I'm not waiting
around, I'm done, he doesn't show up, so you know besides that
we don't know who's חייב, chayav, I mean that's not my point,
my point is nobody was עושה oseh it חמץ. chametz. Right, now
if let's say were in the middle of לישה lishah and you
hadn't finished לישה lishah and you walked away then maybe we could
say you were you were לשת lashet חמץ chametz because it was
still part of that process, I don't know but I'm saying that
we should think about. But it is exactly correct that the issue
here is not to let it become חמץ chametz but to be
עושה oseh it. So you could imagine that it becomes חמץ chametz
because people walked away and nobody was עושה oseh it חמץ. chametz.
And I guess you're doing the parallel to the כהנים kohanim but
by כהנים kohanim we tell him that even if he's בא, ba,
he's right next to the מת meis right now, he still has
to leave, he can't continue to just stay there passively even though
he's not doing any action of bringing himself to טומאה. tumah.
Right, so that's a good example, but that so again the question
is how you conceptualize staying there as continuing to be מטמא, mitamei,
right, or do you consider you know, so all of those how
do you conceptualize those. Okay, but that this is a great גמרא
Gemara because the answer is not the same universally. Every single הלכה
halakhah you have to ask yourself is the focus don't create this
bad end result or is the focus don't do this action, and
then you also have to ask as Mordechai, you know, as this
discussion has shown, what defines doing the action, right, does standing in
a room with a מת meis is that considered an action of
being מטמא, mitamei, is standing around not doing anything considered being
עושה oseh it חמץ, chametz, right, all of these are questions how
do you define.
What if I add another log to the fire so it you
know bakes more quickly am I also getting מלקות malkos on that?
Okay, so Directly we're going to see a little bit about something
related to that as well, about helping the baking of the bread,
yeah.
Okay, surprised there's no discussion whether or not let's say the last
person is aware that it's become חמץ. chametz.
Well right, that would that could be and therefore it would be
a שוגג shogeg or an אונס ones case. But that's not so
much the interest of the גמרא, Gemara you're right. In the case
where he had no reason to suspect otherwise and he was right
to assume everything was done correctly because you know I can assume
you guys are doing your job do also כהנים Kohanim and so
on or whatever the case might be, yeah, so then he would
be an אונס. ones. But that's like less of the concern of
the גמרא. Gemara Of course we'll always assess level of negligence, intention,
and so on and determine מזיד, meizid, שוגג, shogeg, אונס, ones, how
culpable you are. But what's more interesting for the גמרא right now,
that's always can be considered. And that's true, that would be a
what's it called, an exonerating factor. But what's interesting to the גמרא
is how do you conceptualize the prohibition? Okay? So let's take a
look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now we're going to compare it to
a case of a בכור. bechor. Of a בכור bechor with some
מום mum and making another מום mum in the בכור. bechor. Okay
so let's take a look. בכור שאחזו דם, bechor she-achazo dam, a
בכור bechor firstborn animal not a male son. A firstborn animal has
some type of a blood clot. Okay? And presumably how do you
relieve the blood clot is by letting blood. But your act of
letting blood, you cut it will cause a מום. mum. Okay? Now
depending on where you cut it it might heal. The assumption would
be if you cut it in most places in the body then
it'll heal. But if you cut it in its ear that's a
place where it won't heal and the מום mum will remain. Okay?
So where are you allowed to let the blood and if it
what will be if it will cause a מום. mum. So let's
take a look.
מקיזין אותו את הדם, Makizin oto et hadam, some take out the
word את הדם. et hadam. מקיזין אותו במקום שאין עושין בו מום,
makizin oto bemakom she-ein osin bo mum, ואין מקיזין את הדם, ve-ein
makizin et hadam, ואין מקיזין אותו במקום שעושין בו מום. ve-ein makizin
oto bemakom she-osin bo mum. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rebbe Meir. רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir has a very simple point. You can let the
blood but not if you're going to make a מום. mum. You're
being מטיל מום בבכור. matil mum be-bechor. Okay? וחכמים אומרים, Ve-chachamim omrim,
the חכמים chachamim say, יקיז אף במקום שעושין בו מום, yakiz af
bemakom she-osin bo mum, you can do you can let blood even
if you're making a מום. mum. Why? ובלבד שלא ישחוט על אותו
מום. u-bilvad she-lo yishchat al oto mum. So to be as long
as you don't שחט shecht on the מום. mum. Meaning presumably I'll
first explain it one way then I'm going to explain to you
another way. Presumably they sort of say because we're going to see
in a minute רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
is classic the position of דבר שאינו מתכוין. davar she-eino miskavein. Okay
רש"י Rashi sort of ties it in. You can שחט shecht it
even if it's going to make a מום mum because that's not
your intention. It's אינו מתכוין. eino miskavein.
But there's a rabbinic problem. What's the rabbinic problem? If we let
you now say oh this בכור bechor has a מום mum I
don't I don't have to bring it as a קרבן korban because
הלכה halacha of בכור bechor with a מום mum is you can
eat it at home you don't have to bring it as a
קרבן, korban right? Which is why the כהנים Kohanim were very eager
to have מומים mumim on their בכורות bechoros which we run when
we do בכורות. bechoros. So therefore what's going to happen? You know
I let you do this and it is now legitimate to go
ahead. Next time every כהן is going to claim oh that מום
mum that's because I had to let blood. Oh that מום mum
that's because I had to let blood you know and therefore it'll
be a big loophole. People would just claim to have let blood.
So therefore we're saying you're not allowed to שחט shecht on that
מום. mum. What it also does by the way, right you understand
how you don't want to close people's ability to claim that the
מום mum came because they were letting blood.
Oh I'm sorry meaning in regular בכור bechor you bring it you
give it to the כהן.
You give it to a כהן. We now the כהן has the
בכור. bechor. Okay?
Does he have to bring it as a קרבן? korban Which is
the normal הלכה. halacha. Or can he just שחט shecht it and
eat it at home? If it had the מום mum he can
just שחט shecht it and eat it at home. Very nice he
doesn't have to שלעפ schlep all the way to ירושלים Yerushalayim from
תל אביב Tel Aviv or באר שבע Be'er Sheva you know.
So what would
anyone say that you know if you have a choice you can
even make it on a place where it would make a מום?
mum?
Well so well the point is that they're basically saying that it's
אינו מתכוין eino miskavein it's not a big deal.
And they won't be able to bring it as a קרבן korban
right?
No no if it gets another מום mum oh so now now
you're stuck. Now you can't bring it as a קרבן because it
has a מום. mum. You can't שחט shecht it because you're not
allowed to use this מום mum for rabbinic concerns. You're right in
a way it makes life very difficult because now you have to
wait till it gets another מום mum until you can use it.
But look that's also creates a good disincentive to even if it
genuinely does does need the blood let you know with these consequences
you're going to try to do it in a place שאינו עושה
בו מום. she-eino oseh bo mum. Right? So that's also true. And
by the way I should say that's part of the problem here
by using the אינו מתכוין eino miskavein argument. It's very nice that
it's אינו מתכוין eino miskavein but פסיק רישא psik reisha is definitely
going to
happen. Right? You're doing it in a place where עושה מום. oseh
mum. I could wonderful it's אינו מתכוין eino miskavein it's פסיק רישא.
psik reisha. But if I actually say that you're not going to
and this is not how the normal explanation but I'm adding this
as a layer. If you're going to say that you can't שחט
shecht על אותו מום al oto mum you can't use the מום
mum it's פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה. psik reisha d'lo nicha lei.
And not only that as Michael just pointed out correctly it's now
you're now worse off. You can't bring it as a קרבן and
you can't שחט shecht it at home until we get another מום.
mum. So certainly a פסיק רישא psik reisha that you don't want.
So therefore we allow you to go ahead and do it but
you won't benefit from the consequences. That's what the חכמים Chachamim say.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbe Shimon omer, now רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says,
אף on נ"ו עמוד ב, nun vav amud bet, אף נשחט על
אותו מום. af nishchat al oto mum. You can even שחט shecht
on that מום. mum. I do not make rabbinic safeguards. I'm not
concerned somebody is going to deceive and trick etc. Now of course
the big problem for רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is is that now
it's forget telling you it's אינו מתכוין eino miskavein but it's a
פסיק רישא. psik reisha. It's definitely going to result, why is that
allowed? So we will see actually in a minute that the גמרא
is not going to interpret this about מתכוון miskaven and אינו מתכוון
eino miskaven and it's going to interpret it in a way that's
more relevant for our concerns. So let's keep on going. רבי יהודה
אומר Rabbi Yehuda Omer אפילו מת אין מקיזין לו את הדם. afilu
meit ein makizin lo et ha-dam. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even
if it'll die because of this blood clot, you can't let blood,
and you can't let blood even where it won't make a מום.
mum. Why not? Because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has the opposite concern.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says once I let you let blood where
it won't make a מום, mum, you're going to be so anxious
and concerned or whatever, you're going to let blood even where it
does make a מום, mum, and that would be a prohibition. Of
course the response back is, if you're not going to let the
guy do anything, he's going to totally disregard any rules and he's
going to go ahead and not pay attention. If you let him
do it but within certain parameters, he'll be able to be careful.
Okay, to that's a range of rabbinic concerns. Do we let you
use the מום mum afterwards? Do we tell you don't do anything
because we don't trust you? But at least within the case, there
is the position of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that say even though you're doing the מום mum it's okay. And
the question is why? So the גמרא let's take a look at
what the גמרא is going to say about this and how it's
relevant. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, הכל מודים
hakol modin דמחמץ אחר מחמץ de-mechameitz achar mechameitz שחייב. she-chayav. Everybody agrees
that if you make the מנחה Mincha חמץ chametz after it's already
חמץ, chametz, so then you are חייב, chayav, דאית על לישה ואפייה
ואריכה de-it al lisha v'afiya v'aricha for the reasons that we said.
It's not about letting it become חמץ, chametz, it's making it as
חמץ, chametz, and therefore even if it's already חמץ, chametz, any improvement
later in the stage is still making it as חמץ. chametz. So
everybody agrees that that is
חייב. chayav. דכתיב de-chtiv the פסוק pasuk says לא תאפה חמץ, lo
te'afeh chametz, don't make and don't bake, and from that we learn,
as we talked before, that every stage of the process you're חייב
chayav and even if it is already חמץ. chametz. Okay, so that's
what we already said and as I said, it's not about letting
it become a חמץ, chametz, it's about making it. So now we
go on. ובמסרס אחר מסרס u-v'mesares achar mesares שחייב. she-chayav.
Let's say there's a prohibition of
what's the word? Sterilized, not
sterilizing, spaying, yeah, spaying, is that the word? Neutering, maybe.
Anyway, castrating I think, which is a little more graphic but that's
a little more specific to what we're saying, castrating your animals. Okay,
now let's say somebody castrates after castrated.
What does it mean?
Let's say, so רש"י Rashi explains it is, is that the first
person
basically detaches the, I'm forgetting the word here,
the, not the scrotum, what's how do you describe what's in the
scrotum? The testicles, the testicles. I don't know what happened sometimes my
brain
travels on the other end.
One person just, one person detaches the testicles and the next person,
but they were still in the scrotum, and the next person came
along and detached the scrotum. Or the way תוספות Tosafot says, one
person partially detaches the testicles and the other fully detaches. And now
there, my God, if there was any place I would say that
it matters about the result, it would be there. Like, what did
the next person do? It was already, that organ had already stopped
to be functioning. What do I care if you further remove it?
But believe it or not, the גמרא says הכל מודים hakol modin
דמסרס אחר מסרס, de-mesares achar mesares,
that if one person did and the next person did a finish
the job, as it were, or did a second stage, שחייב, she-chayav,
you are חייב. chayav. דכתיב de-chtiv ומעוך וכתות ונתוק וכרות, u-ma'uch v'chatut
v'natuk v'charut, and crushed and cut and נתוק natuk and כרות, karut,
anyway, different ways of distressing, destroying, you know, that organ and the
testicles and all of those things. So the ברייתא braita says, the
מדרש הלכה midrash halacha says, אם על כרות הוא חייב על נותק
ועל כבוש לא כל שכן? im al karut hu chayav al notek
v'al kavush lo kol sheken? If you're חייב chayav for just a
simple cutting, certainly you're חייב chayav for נותק notek which is like
a full removing. So why does it have to say both?
אלא להביא נותק אחר כרות, ela lehavi notek achar karut, that even
if one guy just did a first stage of removal and the
other guy did a full removal afterwards, the second guy is also
חייב. chayav. Okay, so even though however the two stages go together,
partial removal of testicles and a full removal or first cutting the
testicles and then cutting off the scrotum, either way, we're learning from
this that the second person is חייב. chayav. Now that has got
to be the biggest חידוש chiddush of all here because who the
heck cares? The animal already is sterile and has a non-functioning organ.
But that's what we say. Maybe as Ken hinted what we're being
told is seen as abominable and offensive, maybe is a better word,
is seen as offensive even if it's not having the
same effect,
even if it is actually already mutilation.
Right, that's the point. Meaning as I'm saying, that's really why I
was using the word castrating, that it's not just about making the
animal sterile, right, it's about a sense of mutilating the animal and
therefore there's an aspect of mutilation that still occurs even if it's
already been mutilated once, it's being further mutilated next. Okay, so everybody
agrees שחייב. she-chayav. לא נחלקו lo nechleku only at the date, אלא
במטיל מום בבעל מום. ela b'matil mum b'baal mum. If an animal
already has a מום mum and you're going ahead and you want
to make another מום mum in it, by the בכור, bechor, you're
not allowed to make a מום mum in a בכור, bechor, what
if it already has a מום? mum? So there you understand, on
the one hand, if it's the idea is going to find you
a way that you can offer it על המזבח al ha-mizbe'ach and
you're taking something perfect and you're making it less perfect. Obviously if
it already has a מום, mum, it's already not perfect. What do
I care? On the other hand, maybe nevertheless,
actively making a מום mum in something with קדושת קרבן kedushat korban
is seen as an offense, even if because of the מום mum
the קרבן can no longer be brought. So let's take a look.
אלא במטיל מום בבעל מום. ela be-matil mum be-ba'al mum. Rebbe Meir
סבר כל מום לא יהיה בו. savar kol mum lo yihiyeh bo.
This Torah says, 'No blemish should be in it.' And by the
way, everybody should be very happy, it's this week's פרשה. parashah. So
you have some דרוש drush with it, or whatever. So Rebbe Meir
says,
'No blemish should be in it.' Right. So any, meaning even if
it already has a blemish, כל מום kol mum means even another
blemish, even a blemish on top of a blemish.
We're talking about a בכור bechor now, okay?
On a בכור, bechor, right? ורבנן סברי תמים יהיה לרצון, ve-rabbanan savari
tamim yihiyeh le-ratzon,
that no, the contrast to כל מום לא יהיה בו kol mum
lo yihiyeh bo is תמים יהיה לרצון. tamim yihiyeh le-ratzon.
So therefore, only if your מום mum is preventing it from being
תמים. tamim. If it's already no longer תמים, tamim, then there's no
prohibition of making another מום. mum. ורבי מאיר נמי הכתיב תמים יהיה
לרצון? ve-rabbi meir nami ha-ketiv tamim yihiyeh le-ratzon? Doesn't it say it
should be תמים? tamim? ההוא למיעוטי בעל מום מעיקרא. hahu le-mi'utei ba'al
mum me-ikara. No, that is if it was born with a מום
mum or was sanctified, either if it's a בכור bechor if it
was born with a מום, mum, if it's not a בכור bechor
then if it was sanctified with a מום. mum. So in those
cases, there you have no prohibition of a מום. mum. Why? Because
when it starts with that, the קדושה... kedushah when it starts with
that, the קדושה kedushah is of a different level. It never had
קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf or it never had a קדושה kedushah which
was ראוי ra'uy to be brought על המזבח. al ha-mizbe'ach. So the
idea of a מום mum is different than when it started with
that קדושה kedushah, and now a מום mum came and prevented it.
Okay. So... the Gemara says, one minute. That you don't even need
a פסוק pasuk for. בעל מום מעיקרא דקלא בעלמא הוא. ba'al mum
me-ikara dikla be-alma hu. If it started with a מום, mum, it
might as well be a palm tree. Okay, which isn't exactly true.
It still has קדושה, kedushah, but the point is, there was never
a הוה אמינא. hava amina. If it never had קדושה, kedushah it
was never ראוי למזבח, ra'uy le-mizbe'ach, then the גמרא takes it for
granted that there is no prohibition of giving a מום. mum. You
don't need a פסוק pasuk, to exclude that. אלא, okay, so what
does he do with it? למיעוטי פסולי המוקדשים. le-mi'utei psulei ha-mukdashim.
So what does Rebbe Meir say תמים יהיה לרצון? tamim yihiyeh le-ratzon?
That comes to tell you to exclude the case of when an
animal was invalid. Meaning, what happened? Let's say an animal was invalid.
Actually, the best case would be that an animal had a מום
mum and I went ahead and I redeemed it. Okay, not a
בכור. bechor. You don't redeem a בכור, bechor, you just eat it
בגבולין. ba-gvulin. But a normal animal I sanctified. This פסוק about not
putting a מום mum is not limited to a בכור. bechor. Okay,
so it's any קדשים. So I went ahead, I had my עולה,
it got a מום, mum, I redeemed it. Now the Torah says
that what am I allowed to do? I'm allowed to שחט shecht
it and eat it and so on. It's no longer קדשים, but
I don't... it's not fully חולין. chulin. It has a status of
פסולי המוקדשים psulei ha-mukdashim and the Torah still limits what I can
do with it. וזבחת ואכלת ve-zavachta ve-achalta
and the גמרא says,
you know, וזבחת ולא גיזה ואכלת
ולא חלב.
ve-zavachta ve-lo gizzah
ve-achalta ve-lo chalav.
You can't shear it, you can't milk it, you can only שחט
shecht it and eat it. Okay, so now the question is according
to Rebbe Meir that normally says there's a prohibition of מטיל מום
אחר מום, matil mum achar mum, what would he say about this
animal, which has already had its קדושה kedushah. removed, but there are
still some limits? Is there still a prohibition of being מטיל מום
matil mum in this animal? And that's where he's saying there no,
there תמים יהיה לרצון. tamim yihiyeh le-ratzon. And where the חכמים chachamim
emphasize תמים, tamim, that the prohibition of a מום mum is only
when the animal is already perfect, Rebbe Meir is emphasizing the word
לרצון. le-ratzon. Only when it is sort of in the category of
going על המזבח. al ha-mizbe'ach. Once it's taken away from the sort
of to-be-offered category, there's no longer a prohibition. Okay. So אלא למיעוטי
פסולי המוקדשים אחר פדיון, ela le-mi'utei psulei ha-mukdashim achar pidyon, after they've
been redeemed. סלקא דעתך אמינא, I would have thought,
since you're not allowed to shear them and work them, במום נמי
בצריי, be-mum nami bitzrei,
maybe you can't even make a blemish? So the Rebbe Meir says
you can't make a blemish in a בעל מום ba'al mum that
still has קדושה. kedushah קמשמע לן ka-mashma lan that
if it no longer has the קדושה for המזבח, there's no longer
a prohibition even though there's still restrictions.
Right, so Rebbe Meir says you can...
you can make a... you cannot make a מום mum after a
מום, mum, but you can make a מום mum in פסולי המוקדשים.
psulei ha-mukdashim. That's what he gets from תמים יהיה לרצון. tamim yihiyeh
le-ratzon.
ורבנן ve-rabbanan would say even then.
Or ורבנן ve-rabbanan would say even if it's totally למזבח le-mizbe'ach as
the one that has a מום, mum, and the only problem of
a מום mum for the רבנן rabbanan is if you are taking
away from the תמים יהיה. tamim yihiyeh. Okay, so now let's... and
the פסוק, what I haven't done by the way is connected it
back to the earlier debate. Let's just finish up the logic and
then I'll connect it back. ורבנן נמי הכתיב כל מום לא יהיה
בו, ve-rabbanan nami ha-ketiv kol mum lo yihiyeh bo, no blemish should
be in it, which Rebbe Meir says even a blemish after a
blemish. ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא hahu mibaye leh le-khid'tanya for what we
taught in the ברייתא. braita. וכל מום לא יהיה בו, ve-khol mum
lo yihiyeh bo, no blemish should be in it. אין לי אלא
שלא יהא בו מום, ein li ela she-lo yehe bo mum, I
only know that you can't actively make a blemish. מניין שלא יגרום
לו על ידי אחרים, minayin she-lo yigrom lo al yedei acherim, how
do I know you cannot cause it to come about indirectly? שלא
יניח בצק או דבילה על גבי האוזן, she-lo yani'ach batzek o deveilah
al gabei ha-ozen,
you go ahead and take some nice dough... and you put it
around your בכור'ס bechor's ear, or you take some dates or whatever
דבילה d'veilah is figs or dates, I'm again getting, anyway, whatever, and
you put it around the ear כדי שיבא הכלב ויטלנו k'dei she-yavo
ha-kelev v'yitlenu and the dog will come and he'll take a bite
out of it, right, and then he'll bite and then it'll make
a מום mum in your בכור bechor to